howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show
[Music]
today's guest is David Brin
hello Jim it's nice to be talking to
your brainy and precipitation Saudi ins
it was a futurist the technology
consultant and best-selling author his
Hugo locus and nebula awarded novels
include the postman which was made into
a feature film more or less loosely
based on his novel starring Kevin
Costner I remember seeing that movie I
read several of his novels including the
postman the uplift war earth and
existence and most recently the novella
the loom of Dessalines I pronounce that
yeah so it's a region in Greece yeah
it's actually very nice it was short but
it made you think well it's in my shorts
at one of my short story collections and
actually the short fiction is among the
best stuff in science fiction indeed
david's non-fiction book the transparent
society won the freedom of speech award
beyond his writings David is a busy
speaker the audiences around the world
and serves as a consultant on the future
and technology to both business and
government and if you like such things
which I'm kind of take it or leave it
he's also an energetic and sensible
participant on Facebook I'm assuming
probably on other social media it's
surprisingly sensible actually anyway in
preparing for this episode it went
through quite a bit of babies material
and you know one thing that really stood
out for me was your optimism about our
future and it wasn't a naive tech no
utopian optimism either let's start
there in a society seemingly obsessed
with our problems
where does your optimism come from my
optimism comes from our obsession with
our problems all across human history
it's when civilizations were smug and
did not invest in their creative
minority that's according to Toynbee one
of the world's greatest historians
societies rise when they invest in a
creative rambunctious minority that is
fractious and causes trouble but finds
the mistakes and points
out and they start to fail when they
start ignoring or even killing the
critics
well we're members of the first human
civilization that has made criticizing
Authority a religion how many of you in
the audience raise your hand how many of
you in the audience believe firmly that
you're a rebel who holds authority
figures and elites in suspicion and
looks for things to hold them
accountable for and those few of you who
didn't raise your hand how come you're
so lazy and you thought that I couldn't
see that you didn't raise your hand come
on now it's almost 2020 and I have 20/20
vision no the the point is that
Hollywood is responsible for this
mythology and it's it was American
before Hollywood individualism suspicion
of authority romanticization and belief
in personal eccentricity tolerance
diversity are two new ones that are
added to that list and you find all of
them in almost all Hollywood films what
a lot of members of your audience would
refuse to admit is that they got their
rambunctious eccentricity loving
individualistic suspicion of authority
from all the movies that they watched in
other words they were propagandized into
it by one of the most intensive
propaganda campaigns in human history we
don't recognize that as propaganda
because we agree with it and because
it's hard to imagine it as propaganda I
mean what kind of institution or
nefarious plot would organize a
propaganda campaign to make people
suspicious of nefarious plots not just
movies we also have particularly my
generation I think yours - a true
touchstone is Star Trek right you know
with james t kirk who is a figure of
authority but not a good boy all the
time no he is constantly and here's the
difference between one of many
differences between Star Wars and Star
Trek which I've tabulated in a book
called Star Wars on trial and one is
that when you meet a demagogue
in Star Wars you have to choose
instantly am I going to die for this
demigod or I'm gonna die fighting
against this demigod this is really your
only choice in Star Wars and demigods
are the only things that matter in Star
Trek
whenever the enterprise encounters some
pompous demigod type figure Kirk crosses
his arms it says oh yeah tell us about
it and skepticism not necessarily
hostility because Star Trek to the
enterprise runs into some superior
beings that are decent people but it's
the decency and the tolerance and the
diversity and the willingness to be calm
and maybe have a sense of humor that's
what's distinguishes a good elite from a
bad elite in Star Trek and and
truthfully I think we probably have the
same tendency I tend to divide people
into Star Trek people and Star Wars
people to me it's it's a little more
subtle than that and that is that which
do I go to hoping for a combined child
and adults experience and and something
that's still got some basic decent
morality Star Wars I go to see every
single movie but I go stone because the
special effects of the visuals and the
music are going to be stunning but I
don't want to notice at least the first
time around I don't want to notice the
dismal lessons being taught but and
again the book is called Star Wars on
trial and it's not just the downer
points of view I'm the prosecuting
attorney calling witnesses against Star
Wars but Matthew woodring Stover one of
Lucas's novel eyes errs it was the
defense attorney and he calls and all
sorts of witnesses essayist
writing ins in in favor of Star Wars
it's one of the most fun books I've ever
participated in don't know about am I
go get that one that that sounds very
interesting before we move on from this
point I'm gonna point out you know that
we talked about kind of lowbrow
influences like TV and Hollywood but
also on the higher end Karl Popper wrote
a book which is actually the only
philosophy book that sits in my working
library called the open society and its
enemies where he makes the very deep
point that a society that is open to its
self criticism in pretty arbitrarily
strong ways is a society they can adapt
to reality in a society they can adapt
to reality is a society that can
persevere well yeah I'm a big fan of
popper also as a matter of fact it's
basically the notion that informed my
own non-fiction book the transparent
society will technology make us choose
between privacy and freedom and you know
what all those awards you mentioned but
the main thing is that we both noticed
one fundamental thing and that is that
all of our institutions that have made
us unusual across the history of
humanity they all depend on light we
have five great competitive adversarial
arenas that have harnessed the inherent
creative aspect of competition and Adam
Smith was right competition is the great
creative force of the universe it's how
we came about through natural evolution
competition can be very bloody and very
inefficient but it certainly is creative
we have five arenas that have tried to
harness this creativity of competition
and in ways that maximize the creativity
while minimizing the blood on the floor
these five arenas are commercial markets
and science democracy justice courts and
sports and in all five arenas the aim
was to use rules and umpires to try to
eliminate the factor that destroyed all
these things in the
asked for 6,000 years competition never
reached its potential in any human
society because the winners in
competition then cheated cheating is the
great enemy and and one of the greatest
forms of cheating is feudalism oligarchy
when you have a lot of power you then
manipulate the laws and and pick up
swords and hire people did pick up sores
and take other men's women and wheat and
then you hire a bunch of guys in spangly
robes shamans priests chanters bards to
tell everybody how good this was that
you did that well it's starting with
Adam Smith a little bit before Adam
Smith but he's the one who codified it
and then the American founders pretty
much the same year 1776 they noticed
something and that is something that
Karl Marx thought was impossible and
that is it's possible to set up using
cooperation the co-operative process
called negotiation public open
transparent negotiation to come up with
rules and umpires and referees to keep
these five arenas fair and to damp down
the cheating to a dull roar and the best
example of this is sports try to imagine
any sporting league NBA NFL anything in
which you declare one weekend that all
rules are off there won't be any umpires
and by the way that includes all laws
against murder how many minutes do you
think an NFL game would last yeah that
would not be very interesting it would
just be a rumble essentially right it
would be interesting for the first 10
minutes and then there'd be never any
football played ever again and that
doesn't serve the interest of the owners
what serves the interests of the owners
and the fans and the players is intense
regulation and that's exactly what we
got under FDR during the greatest
generation my parents survived the
depression crushed Hitler contained
Stalinism built the great American
middle class
took us to the moon and started us down
the long grinding path of cleaning our
souls of so many ancient crimes like
racism and sexism and all that crap
The Greatest Generation is admired if
you ask any Mogga hat-wearing person
when we were great they would probably
dame the 50s in the greatest generation
well the greatest generation would spit
in these guys faces and their favorite
human being was called Franklin Delano
Roosevelt and they set up complicated
rules so that we got the best most
creative fastest-growing economy in the
history of the world that shared most of
the benefits with a growing middle class
and the whole aim of the supply-side
revolution has been to tear down
everything the greatest generation built
and bring us back to 6,000 years of
cheating so in any event that was a long
roundabout way to talk about Karl Popper
because popper was talking about much
the same thing how an open society in
which we can criticize each other and
criticize each other's products and
criticize each other's policies or
criticize each other in the courtroom or
criticize each other's scientific
theories that criticism is the only
known antidote to error and all five of
those arenas are creative and productive
and you get what's called the positive
sum game
when these arenas are fleshed clean with
light light light light maximum number
of people knowing maximum about what was
going on most of the time and they are
all five of them poisoned and ruined by
secrecy and darkness and I'm going to
make a point about positive sum game
because some people might say hm that's
kind of hopeful thinking but it's
probably not true but in reality markets
are a good example most people don't
realize this but everybody except the
very last buyer pays less than they'd be
willing right I look at the supply the
curve and the
the man curve they intercept that the
last person that will buy at a price
somebody will supply everybody else gets
what's called the consumer surplus and
it's huge it's where the least
appreciated most important things about
our social operating system that
essentially every economic transaction
occurs at a price lower than the person
would be willing to pay for instance a
computer you know 800 bucks truthfully
if I had to I'd pay twenty five thousand
dollars for this laptop right but
because of supply and demand I don't
have to say no I paid four thousand
dollars for my first computer in 1980
that was you know a billionth is
powerful as this one so we really can
have positive some outcomes from
competitive games which some people just
don't believe is possible well you know
this is a I think the if any of your
audience don't get the notion of
positive something versus zero-sum and
versus negative some actually then that
is the most important concept they can
come away from here and look up and try
to understand and I think it's a miracle
that a large fraction of Americans
especially after all that Hollywood
propaganda a large fraction of them get
the basic notion of positive sum that I
can win while you win I just want to win
a little more than you win and my
striving to win a little more than you
win if it's done fairly in a fair market
and you're striving to win a little more
than I win that we we all win more
because we're doing that now on the Left
there's a little bit of a tendency to
sneer at the word competition and to say
cooperation but we wouldn't get the
rules that make competition work if it
weren't for a cooperative process called
negotiated politics which is also
competitive and we haven't had
Shadid politics in America since 1995
that's the miracle year the last year in
which a Republican leader in Congress
actually cooperated with Democrats
that's the year that Newt Gingrich and
Bill Clinton negotiated welfare reform
and the budget act that led to huge
surpluses the next year Newt was
punished for that kicked out and
replaced by Dennis friend to Boys
Hastert and you should look up why I
used that snark in his name I'm well
aware it was all over the newspapers and
the Hastert rule came down threatening
extinction to any Republican politician
who would even speak of negotiation with
a member of the opposition and politics
in America a noble art was destroyed and
that was how many years ago that was 26
years ago a little bit less 24 well in
any event the point is that the notion
of the positive sub game is based upon
one word that the left doesn't
particularly like but should be taught
to like because the founder of
competition Theory who warned against
cheating by oligarchs and aristocrats
was the father of modern liberalism and
his name was Adam Smith if he were alive
today Adam Smith would be a flaming
Democrat people who think otherwise have
never read the man so what's tragic is
Democrats or liberals crowning at the
word competition and conservatives
frowning at the word regulation when if
you look at all five of those arenas its
regulated competition that has given us
for the first time in the history of our
species the ability to avoid cheating
and to maximize the positive some
fecundity of markets and democracy in
science and justice courts and sports
and all of them are horribly imperfect
all of them need tweaking and and the
regular
need to be refined and sometimes they
need to be tossed out you deregulate
some more hoody regulates more it's
Democrats because they got rid of the
Interstate Commerce Commission that Iran
hated they got rid of the Civil
Aeronautics Board they broke up AT&T Al
Gore's bill was what freed us up freed
up the internet that we know today it
could have been very very different he
could have been a public utility here
Bill Clinton liberated GPS and Obama
declared that citizens have a universal
right to record their interactions with
police
so deregulation isn't a monopoly of
those who scream for deregulation yep
and I would before we move on here I'm
gonna point out that part of the
confusion around Adam Smith is people
who've only read The Wealth of Nations
now he does make some of the counter
arguments there but if you want to see
the other side of Adam Smith in its pure
form you really should read the book the
Theory of Moral Sentiments I highly
recommend that yes I totally agree
that's a that's a deeply deeply caring
and moral man who praises charity and
and state intervention to help the poor
but he makes clear in Wealth of Nations
the fundamental justification for most
liberal interventions in politics in the
economy is not goody-two-shoes morality
I really get impatient with Democrats
and liberals who proclaim that every one
of their programs can be justified
because it's the moral and right thing
to do well the answer to that is well
that's what you say but my morality is
different it has too easy a refutation
these programs the ones that help
children to grow up stronger and more
educated and more confident they have a
totally capitalistic justification and
that's stop wasting talent maximize the
number of citizens and consumers who can
participate knowingly and intelligently
in competitive
markets and the only way to do that is
to make fear the children all get enough
protein and all get educated and get
healthcare it's the failure of liberals
to justify their interventions by the
totally pragmatic outcomes that they
generate I mean do you remember the
movie deliverance
oh yeah the image that we have The
Beverly Hillbillies image of the
Appalachia gap-toothed ignorant
illiterate
well Appalachia has problems today right
now they're fighting opioids and and and
they're not rich people but it's a
different world it's a totally different
part of America because America came in
and said hey you're Americans and we
haven't forgotten you actually live in
Appalachia my official residence is in
the lowest population density counties
east of the Mississippi River and the
people there are very good and very
solid and have good Civic values an
amazing statistic is the election
turnouts are between 75 and 80 percent
100 percent of the kids graduate from
high school you know the stereotypes can
be quite misleading actually and I am
proud that we're a nation that has taken
some of those stereotypes and changed
them physically on the ground there's a
lot of federal funding that comes into
the county there's no doubt about it but
on the other hand it's still a
hard-working make them you know make
money from the land farming logging some
recreation etc can I bless you wear it
wear it wherever you are yeah that's a
good spot
let's go continue on the theme of
optimism you know I've read
heard you in some of your recordings say
that you agree with Steven Pinker and
others who published findings about how
the world is improving in many ways
could you give us a quick overview of
the most important points of good news
oh well I recommend everybody to
subscribe to the abundance newsletter of
Peter Diamandis yeah he's the guy who
runs the X prizes and the X prizes are
aimed at finding ways to leverage just a
million dollars here a million dollars
there to incentivize tens and even
hundreds of millions of dollars of
investment with prizes in world changing
world savings solutions one of them I
participated in was the tricorder X
Prize to try to develop a version of dr.
McCoy's Star Trek tricorder that would
just add a couple of instruments to a
cell phone and turn it into a primitive
early version of what he used uses in
the show to diagnose illnesses and all
of that look many wonderful things are
happening Dean Kamen's and many others
are developing desalinization systems
Elon Musk is delivering electric cars
and helping push along solar energy and
giving us access to space Jeff Bezos is
racing out there and investing in
asteroid mining along with Peter
Diamandis there are many many wonderful
things in the world but my biggest
reason for saying that is not optimism
I'm actually a little offended when I'm
called an optimist because if you read
my works you'll know that I'm very
nervous
I look at the world around me and
because I am steeped in history not so
much of my physics background or my work
with NASA
it's the history that shows me how
easily we could plummet back into the
hell my ancestors strove for 6,000 years
to get me out of and the fact that I
live in these
comforts and get to talk to youth and
your audience the way I am right now
that I would be anything but grateful
and nervous that it all could be lost
and that's the sense that you get from
my novel The Postman we're in all of it
did get lost and I take a different
perspective than most of the Mad Max
stories the postman is about how the
only way we'll ever get anything back is
not from some lone hero but if we're all
reminded that we were once mighty beings
called citizens and that's what we need
right now because we could solve so many
more problems if citizenship were our
central agenda and we hammered the
politicians till they went back to pre
1995 and went back to negotiating the
reason why I push optimism is because
both sides are insane
today's right is trying to ignore
problems that could kill us all
and today's left thinks the only way we
can motivate people to solve those
problems is guilt trips and they feed on
each other and many Republicans stay
Republicans just to spite the guilt
trippers they know their side has gone
insane but the guilt-tripping is
loathsome to them and so it's bites
those people and so they stay in the
denying climate change for that reason
and quite frankly at times I don't blame
them well I do because it can kill my
children but I understand it the point
is that the left their addiction to
guilt trips is insane and not justified
if you look at how they treated Steven
Pinker for his book the better angels of
our nature throwing so many pieces of
good news 90% of children today
come home with schoolbooks to hovels
that we would consider grinding poverty
but those hovels have a flush toilet a
refrigerator and electric lights to
study by and enough food to get by every
day 90% that's never been true before
90% of human beings today have never
seen war with their own eyes they've
never heard the tramping of an invading
army they've never smelled a burning
city 90% the remaining 10% in each
category is horrible it should tear at
our conscience it should it should
propel us to be desperate to improve
more but we don't get motivated by total
gloom if nothing we have done across the
last 80 years did any good at all why
bother but the truth is the things that
we've done across the last 80 years were
fantastic they were fabulous we sold
half of the world's problems and if we
don't solve the other half we're all
going to die but that first half should
give us confidence that we can that it's
possible and that's the sales pitch that
liberals should be pushing their attacks
on Steven Pinker and Peter Diamandis for
saying there is good news those attacks
are treason and I will say you know sort
of by necessity I found myself voting
blue the last 27 years because the other
side has just gotten too crazy but I've
never signed on to the whole blue team
stuff in particular in 2016 I saw a lot
of other wise sensible people voting for
Trump only in response to what you might
call extreme political correctness and
you know people being shamed for not
using exactly the right word for the
exact
the right thing and it's like what the
hell these people have no idea what the
real world is like and you know I've
been warning for years that this new
obsessed version of identity politics
which isn't about you know redressing
grievances a separate group is was gonna
produce Oh a backlash from the biggest
identity group of all which is exactly
what happened yes well you know look I
map things differently than left and
right because the old values of left and
right really don't map very well on what
we see today the way I see it is that
America and under America's influence
the west and Hollywood's influence
America has a great project and that is
expanding our horizons expanding our
horizons of opportunity to include new
scientific breakthroughs new products
new places where we can go and and get
rich and and and raise families like
asteroid mining and by the way don't get
me started on this insane notion of
Americans going back physically to the
moon this project also includes
expanding our horizons of tolerance and
inclusion and it's been going on since
1776 those geniuses expanded the circle
of political inclusion of empowerment
from 0.2% of the population under the
kings of England to 20% of the
population land owning white
english-speaking males well from our
perspective as members of the
civilization that they built we consider
that to be horrible and we see that all
the time if you compare any era of
America to what came later they were
nasty if you compare them to what came
before they were geniuses and moral
people who push things forward and so 30
years later the Jacksonian Revolution in
the Appalachians empowered the
scots-irish
and small farmers we fought a terrible
civil war to free a millions of people
from bondage and then we lost the next
phase of the civil war
phase five the reconstruction by not
helping those former slaves to become
equal citizens this expansion project
think of it as an expanding shell around
the fire light and when women got
included it was a huge step forward but
as with you know minority Americans the
definition of inclusion had to keep
getting redefined well my left right and
middle view of our politics is fairly
simple what we call leftist they give
their national identity their sense of
patriotic vigor not to the United States
of America but to that forward IDI that
project itself is what they are devoted
to and when they feel that there's been
empowerment given to one minority group
they'll find another and yes it can get
very sanctimonious that's and it is also
zero sum which means that they look at
people who like their old loyalties as
betraying this new loyalty of tolerance
and expansion the right in America is as
you say Jim they're saying get out of my
face with all that I I expanded my
tolerance last year excuse me I gave at
the office too and I have to do it every
month I like my flag I liked going to
the boys club and my wife can vote and
tell me what to do but I like going to
the boys club then there is a third
category and these are liberals and they
are actually the largest group in
America and they are the only one of the
three that's positive some and they say
hey I don't have to choose I love this
country I like my flags
I like the Boy Scouts and we're going to
slowly ratchet them into including
and I also like this project of
expansion horizons
tell me more but I think it might be a
good idea if you were a little more
polite the problem with these PC bullies
is not that they are doing a lot of harm
they're not but they are giving Fox
heads ammo every night and the what they
say what Hannity says is do you see
these flaming political correct police
that's what all liberals are like and
it's a lie but what surprised I mean Fox
it's a lie sorry I was getting
repetitious there yep and it certainly
hasn't helped I'm sorry you know what we
should have saved politics for the end
yeah let's move on to some other things
here this is sort of near politics but
it gets back to systems thinking which
is the web you know I was one of the
early people that helped build what
became the web and was involved in it
for much of my business career and we
thought frankly that we were both doing
well and doing good that this ought to
be the mechanism for empowered
citizenship everybody has access to
information can communicate to the
powers that be
etc and yet at the moment it seems like
a real shitstorm right really bad and
stupid ideas you're making a big
comeback
I mean Nazis I mean what the hell right
Nazis are coming back can you imagine a
stupider idea than that well maybe one
flat earthers right they're coming back
anti-vaxxers right you know there's
something about this new unmediated form
of communication that we did not see
when we were creating it that is
producing a standing wave of some sort
that's allowing really bad
to gain some traction now personally I'm
not as an alarmist as some people are I
just I do believe that Nazis are not
gonna take over America nor our flat
earthers gonna take over our school
system but it is nonetheless pretty
disconcerting that there are you know
significant numbers of people adhering
to these unbelievably backward ideas any
thoughts to what's going on with this
yeah well first off let's always look
for a historical perspective historical
perspective number one is that it's not
unprecedented for the oligarchic
aristocratic cheaters to try to use
populism against reformers this happened
against the rocky Brothers in in Rome
and during the 1920s and early 30s the
Yonkers cast of nobles in Germany who
had a lot of the money and owned the
newspapers they promulgated Nazism
because they wanted to use it as a
weapon against the Communists and of
course you remember the scene in the
tomorrow belongs to me scene from
cabaret in which the question is asked
do you still think you can control them
and they wound up not they wound up
creating a monster a beast that through
the aristocratic riders and gifted
finales jumped into the saddle and and
wrote us all to hell we can see
parallels now I mean the Republican
Party you know the people who the old
line conservatives and the oligarchs who
brought us to this point are rising in
agony because they can see something
very similar happening but it gets to
talk about the web you know you say who
foresaw this well I have a novel called
earth and I have a
called the transparent society and in
both of those I talked about how every
time there is a new communication
technology
this happens when printing presses were
invented we have this image of Gutenberg
Bibles but the biggest product for about
50 years
was hateful religious tracts that
exacerbated the Catholic versus
Protestant wars that tore Europe from
stem to stern it was only after time
passed that books spread and people used
literacy to start expanding their calm
consideration of bigger ideas in a
bigger world and that took a long time
but the same thing happened with
magazines and newspapers and the biggest
example was when radios and loudspeakers
arrived and these expanded the apparent
godlike force of the human voice and in
the twenties and early thirties these
two new technologies were exploited by
gifted polemicists who exploited this
godlike expansion of their voice to
drive their populations mad and the only
real difference in the english-speaking
world in America and Britain is that the
the gifted polemicists who we chose and
that's the operative word because if we
democratically chose them we're on our
side Roosevelt Churchill they were
really good at sounding godlike but they
also were on our side and that made a
huge difference so you know does that
have lessons for today duh you know in
early 2017 I spoke to some executives at
Facebook who were terribly worried about
what they had participated in all the
malignant memes and all of that and I
showed them a dozen ideas for how to use
competitive processes
to staunch bad ideas because that's what
the Internet should be it should be our
sixth competitive creative positive-sum
Arena markets mediate competition in
ritualized combat called stores and in
the marketplace over products and goods
and services
democracy is ritualized combat over
policies or at least it's supposed to be
and it used to be and it could be again
sciences ritualized combat over models
of the world justice courts are highly
ritualized combat over the functional
truth of civil or criminal law and
sports of course are ritualized combat
period well among the ideas that I
presented was dispute Asian arenas
methods by which we could solve some of
these problems not with a Ministry of
Truth to decide what's true and what's
not true but competitively by creating
methods of ritualized combat that would
actually do something that the internet
has never done and that's destroy
falsehoods and we are so used to it
being incapable of doing that that we
assume it's incapable of doing that now
did Facebook pick up and use any of the
ideas I gave them yeah sounds like
possibly an interesting idea though I
mean it's in the group of some people I
hang out with they use a phrase called
sense making as the name for it still
ill-defined process by which we can
collectively sort through what's
floating around in the InfoSphere and
and make some determinations some
discernments about what is true what is
not true or what is indeterminate but I
have yet to see a mechanism that can
actually do that at scale yes well you
know the point is you need to step back
and look at what the all all the other
five arenas did and what all the other
five arenas do
they have a bi-phase process there is a
centrifugal phase in which the
participants the combatants can go and
prepare and this includes the company
and their research labs in science it's
the tenured faculty position and the and
the secure lab and in democracy it's the
political party in courts it's
attorney-client leverage in sports it's
the training ground but all of them have
then a centripetal or inward drawing
called to combat ritual combat and those
arenas of ritual combat are the
marketplace the scientific conference or
publication the election and the
courtroom and the sporting field and you
cannot refuse the ritualized combat no I
won't bring this product to market yeah
that'll show you what we need is a way
to a have ritualised combats online that
actually have credibility that actually
are well enough watched and well enough
respected that when the combat is done
and it can take us in it I have a paper
about this look up disputation arenas in
my name that when all is said and done
after a year there is a generalized
consensus that somebody won and but
here's the more important thing both
sides have altered their positions under
the brunt of criticism and that's some
more likely outcome think of gun control
I mean if you had any people with
intellectual honesty no matter what
their starting positions on gun control
I predict that their positions would be
both sides would be substantially
changed within a few months of this
process but then there's the question is
how do you compel them to come to this
arena or how do you compel anyone to pay
attention that's the real problem
well those those are
problems if people paid attention then
advocates would come I mean we live in
an attention economy above all else
right you're absolutely right and so
what like in many problems in society
today this would take a millionaire or a
deca millionaire probably a cent a
millionaire or well he'd have to be able
to come up I was worked it out it would
take about five million dollars to get
this rolling you know there are so many
things there's so much money in that
upper caste and many of them do not like
where things are going they can see that
if you wind up where we will be so we're
fifty families have more money than the
bottom three billion people that you're
heading into territory that's a lot like
France in 1789 Moscow in 1917 and what
you need at times like this is what we
got in 1776 in 1860 but more importantly
in 1898 and in and during the greatest
generation and that is calmer resets and
we can get calm resets they might look
on paper pretty drastic your audience
would probably be surprised to learn and
the tea party was such a wedged
phenomenon and it was all the Liberals
fault for lowing these fanatics to
hijack the American Revolution of all
things which was a revolution against
feudalism it wasn't against government
it was against feudalism it was against
the king and his cronies stifling trade
and making all the Boston and New York
and Philadelphia merchants send their
ships to the Kings docks and and have an
N and extorting bribes from them that's
why it was Boston and Philadelphia and
New York that led the revolution well if
you'd like to take a look at what
happened after the Revolution was over
it's astonishing
the founders seized
between a quarter and a third of all the
land in the former colonies from their
owners and redistributed it it was one
of the biggest wealth
redistributions in the history of
humanity and hardly anybody knows about
it another one happened four score and
seven years later when the property of a
quarter of a million slave holders was
expropriated from them and redistributed
to the bodies and minds of the property
itself compared to that FDR was nothing
nothing and the greatest the greatest
generation did a lot of stuff and they
deserve our respect and they were
believers in Roosevelt ISM at least a
majority of the more there was always a
substantial opposition class but
certainly the the Roosevelt Ian
consensus controlled 55% of the
electorate maybe a little more until
about 1965 or thereabouts well we all
know about the how Johnson knew that the
South was being given as a gift to the
Republican Party and basically what we
were had we were experiencing was a
party flip what none of us expected was
the radicalization that led to a
destruction of negotiated politics you
know that the same year that Newt
Gingrich was the last Republican to
negotiate important bills with Bill
Clinton with a Democrat the Senators
Tsongas and Rudman were almost complete
with entitlement reform a bill that
would have secured Social Security
Medicare secured their finances until
maybe 2080
and this is something that the right has
railed that we need and yet they're the
ones that torpedoed it in any event
let's severe away from party politics
let's move on to another very
interesting topic that you've written
and
talked a lot about which is the
transparent society you know I actually
started to read that book the
transparent society and I read a little
bit in the in the front several pages
and then I realized man this is really
old so let's talk about it but
nonetheless it's a little bit I read you
are extremely prescient you're going oh
my god the UK has three hundred thousand
CCTV cameras right crime is plummeting
now they have 5.9 million you talked
about cheap drones you even talked about
drones that would fit in your hand and
this was in 1997 maybe something like
that well not only that but if you look
on page 160 there's a scene in which a
cop pulls over a ghetto youth and the
cop has a camera on his shoulder patting
about and transmitting to the station
house and the youth gets out and has a
camera panning on his shoulder
transmitting back to his home computer
VCR unit well like all very good
predictions it's also hilarious the
cameras are not on the shoulders the
police have them sort of near their
badge and the thing we desperately need
is a lapel camera that uses the watch
technology to connect to the phones so
that these youths can be hands-free
because their lives depend on it
but one of my beefs against the news
media is their addiction to gloom and
bad news not only harms our morale but
it hides from us important events 2013
was the most important year for civil
liberties in America in this century so
far and that was when President Obama
and the courts together declared a
universal right of citizens when they're
not directly interfering to record all
interactions with the police it was of
incredible importance
because where else are you going to have
more important interactions with
authority than with the people with guns
and nightsticks and don't let the
lefties fool you that this camera
footage has made no difference it's made
a big difference a hell of a lot of good
cops out there have now decided my
career and maybe my life is being
jeopardized by the bad apples in our
barrel and they're being pushed out not
as fast as we want reforms never happen
as fast as we want but as Martin Luther
King said the arc is bending and the
thing that helps the arc is very often
technology Martin Luther King would have
gotten nowhere without the primitive TV
and film cameras that followed him
around and recorded bull Connor's dogs
attacking in the fire hoses now is the
technology going to be enough by itself
have you seen what's going on in China
with social credit they are not only
putting cameras everywhere controlled by
the top which is what I criticized in
the transparent society but they're also
getting people to tattle on each other
in order to keep their social credit
scores high this was very very
shockingly illustrated in Charlie
broker's wonderful episode of Black
Mirror are called downfall oh yes that
was shockingly good yes very good so the
thing is that you know sure they're
prescient passages in the transparent
Society for many years I got P 206
emails pointing me to page 206 of the
transparent society where I used the
phrase what if bombers ever brought down
both World Trade Center towers this was
in 1997 so that was a Twilight Zone
moment interesting let's get back to
that core argument that you make in that
book and made from time to time
elsewhere is there's two models how this
transparent society could deal with the
information that is created and one as
you could go to the powers that be or
the second it could be open source so
far from what I've seen all this
surveillance society which is another
you know perhaps less positive term for
it is going to the powers that be either
to the police or the three-letter
intelligence agencies for on one side or
to the for-profit corporations they're
capturing our behavioral data exhaust on
social media none of these know this
information is going into the Commons
could you speak to whether that's still
a feasible ambition first of all I urge
people who are being critical to stop
and look in the mirror your reflex is to
worry about accumulations of power bi
would be Big Brother's you were trained
to have that reflex and it's a very good
reflex it's a very American one and it's
very important for our freedom that we
have it but the problem is that when we
ignore the fact that we have it and that
others have it too we reduce our power
to actually use it properly
it's like liberals refusing to admit
there's been any good news this reflex
to criticize is vital and we need to
recognize it in each other it used to be
that the chief difference between a
decent Democrat and a decent Republican
is which direction they think elites are
conniving to become Big Brother the
conservative thinks it's snooty
academics and faceless government
bureaucrats the liberal thinks it's
conniving oligarchs and hazus
corporations it happens that you know
and and in good times and normal
the proper answer is duh you're both
right because connivers and cheaters
will go to wherever they see an
opportunity and the proper role of a
decent Democrat and a decent Republican
is to guard each other's backs
I don't agree with you that my elites
are that dangerous but you keep an eye
on them for me I'm going to after your
elites and that would be a very
reasonable thing to do and we have done
that at intervals in our republic and
that synergy is exactly what the
oligarchs have been conniving to destroy
along with politics in America as we
stand right now I am NOT naturally a
person of the left like you I believe in
Adam Smith I believe in competitive
processes you heard me earlier talk
about that my god and Brynn's talking
about five and maybe six highly
competitive arenas that doesn't sound
very lefty and yet I am forced to
conclude looking at around my nation
right now that the fears of the Liberals
of conniving conspiracies to become Big
Brother by oligarchs and and faceless
corporations is entirely true and the
propaganda motivating the right about
snooty academics and faceless government
bureaucrats is so minimally true that it
we just can't be bothered with it right
now I hate being in that position I am a
contrarian my blog is called contrary
Brin you'll find that I poke at lefties
all the time and on University campuses
they can be real bastards
but I'm sorry we're in phase eight of
the American Civil War and we just have
to choose sides I hate that in any of it
let me back off a second you were asking
about about surveillance yes who
controls the data from conserve
I was lecturing you that you are part of
the process by which we are actually
counterbalancing that but in your
criticism you fail to notice how very
much how very far along we've gone in
sousveillance sou s it's French for
looking back at power from below now I
know a lot of people at the Electronic
Frontier Foundation the ACLU they're
fighting for us and I urge everybody to
join send them your money because
they're fighting for you it's as simple
as that
while you're at it the Sierra Club you
know there's a bunch of things that you
can join an NGO and they'll fight for
you and that's one of the points is
people don't notice the NGOs and they
can pull the dues from their members a
million members and hire technical
people and lawyers as good as any
corporation can hire they can hire
lawyers as good as the government has
and boy do they sow the playing field is
not just you as an individual against
Facebook and the NSA it's you as an
individual who is sent dues to the
Electronic Frontier Foundation against
some of the things being done by the NSA
while many of those civil servants are
also working hard for us against some of
what Facebook is doing it's more
complicated and as long as it's
complicated we have a chance
unfortunately my friends at EF F and the
ACLU they have the right reflex we have
to fight these potential big brothers
who are gathering our information and
then they take it in a wrong direction
they try to pass european-style laws
restricting everybody's ability to see
thou shalt not institute face
recognition that
thou shalt not gather widely available
data that's flowing across the web what
how the hell are you going to do that
you ban face recognition systems and
they're all they'll be on apps next year
you ban people from collecting
information that's flowing like air
around us like water surrounding fish
you cannot show me one example in the
history of the world when laws and rules
for very long blinded for mighty
societies elites they'll refuse it
doesn't work it's never happened if you
go to the zoo and try to poke out the
eyes of the biggest baboon here's a hint
he won't let you but he will grudgingly
let you look at him and that is what we
have experience doing for 250 years it's
looking back at power we can do that we
can do sousveillance
and we know it works because we're free
we're not as free as we'd like to be but
we're freer than our parents were and
they're free they were freer than their
parents and they did it by seeing not by
hiding and cringing from light look
which is more important what it'll
societies elites can know about you or
what they can do to you you're never
going to keep them from knowing stuff
about you but if you know about them and
especially the NGOs that you're a member
of can know all about them then these
elites can't do much to you and that's
the important thing you know I go
another step beyond that though it's
what I call radical transparency which I
take your point that they know all about
why don't we just turn the tables and
say let's know all about everybody they
already know all about us let's know all
about them
well my earlier guess Robin Hanson I
don't know if you know Robin but he
floats all kinds of really interesting
you know outrageous ideas but they're
grounded every time in sort of
fundamental good sense Robin said what
would happen if we mandated publication
of all IRS filings all including
individual tax filings it would have a
fundamental changing of the information
asymmetry today they know about us we'd
suddenly know a shitload about them
how's that not a net gain for the
citizenry well it's exactly what they do
in Estonia and all through Europe a lot
more is public record and we don't bitch
about the fact that our property tax
records are open because we're used to
it you can't sell your home secretly
everyone will know what you got for it
so it's just where you're used to
pegging the line and I totally agree
with you it's more important that we
know about Mark Zuckerberg than futilely
and hopelessly trying to keep him from
knowing about us now what he does with
our information that's a middle ground
that we could do something about we
could if we knew where our information
was going not prevent its use but get
paid for its use that's a whole nother
topic have interest in our information
rather than this silly idea that we'd
own it all the propaganda message of the
movie and the book the circle really
bugged me and there were several places
in in that book in which he but you
could tell from certain passages that he
was having digs at me but many of your
audience and I think they should watch
the movie many of your audience will
recall a scene in which the protagonist
who's gone whole hog into this
cult of this society this company that's
Google and Facebook combined she posts
everything and privacy is stealing and
secrecy is theft her ex-boyfriend comes
to her and begs her to leave him alone
cuz he's a shy guy and while she's
sneering at him her co-workers gather
around and aim their phones at him
posting it online embarrassing the hell
out of him basically driving him up
suicidal again this is a case of looking
in the mirror what was the director and
the screenwriter trying to achieve with
that scene they were trying to tweak the
conscience of the audience to be
repelled by this notion to be repelled
by this behavior therefore the director
and the screenwriter believe that it's
possible that it's likely that decent
people would be propelled by that
behavior hence in that scene if the
camera only peeled back 10 feet you'd
see other people gathering around aiming
their cameras at the bullies because
what they're doing to the shy guy is so
much worse and so much more repulsive
than his refusal to share look at these
bullies look at these assholes driving
this guy to the edge of suicide look at
the who raised these guys I'm sending
images of this to your mom and it never
occurs to anybody that that's the
reaction the director wants
therefore he believes it's possible
therefore it would happen in that film
but that would be an expression of faith
in us rather than contempt in us and it
would certainly be an expression of the
notion that the answer to transparency
bullying is to turn the tables
the bullies and the only way you can get
that is with transparency and that won't
work in China yep China is its own model
and let's hope that it fails but it
might not oh they look look look if
you're going to have a final competition
over the course of human governance for
the next thousand years we've eliminated
some really stupid things but to have it
be a contest between Western diversity
individualism not so much capitalism the
market economy economics is implied by
that versus the best possible example of
the old pyramid hierarchy of rule by
oligarchs one is a classic pyramid of
power topped by an emperor and court
scholars and the other is a diamond
shaped like a diamond vast middle class
the turns and incorporates competition
and in which the leaders are not
consumed to be the state same as the
state in fact they must be recycled
frequently to prevent abuse of power
right now the diamond is suffering from
internal sabotage and external attacks
but I believe in it and I believe in its
resilience and I believe that it is
likely to be the governance model that
will lead to star trek but if we're
going to have a return to 6,000 years of
pyramidal structures which dominated 99%
of countries and societies that had
agriculture and that our enlightenment
is an escape from it might be a brief
escape if we're going to return to that
and I'd prefer China over our own
oligarchs because they have a tradition
of meritocracy civil services
of bringing the brightest up to just a
level below the Emperor and his and his
family that's a better system than say
Pax Britannica or Pax Romana or any of
those systems if we're doomed to become
a hive then I'd rather it be Chinese
bees but I'm going to fight against it
because I believe we have something
special it's called the Enlightenment
experiment and I don't see any other way
we can get to the Stars which actually
raises another question and that's the
Fermi paradox we talk about the Fermi
paradox at about half of our episodes
it's one of the things I asked people
before I interview them are they game to
say something about the Fermi paradox
and actually the show right before
David's these are above gone on the air
yet as we're speaking was a interview
for the full 90 minutes on nothing but
the Fermi paradox with Jill tarter so
our audience knows a fair amount now
about what the Fermi paradox is and why
it's important
David what are your thoughts well first
off Jill's a sweetheart and and one of
the brilliant figures of the field I've
been in SETI now for 35 years in 1983 I
wrote probably the most influential
paper in the field that was the first to
try to tabulate 50 or so explanations or
theories for what was then not called
the Fermi paradox but I called the great
silence which I think is a better word
better term it's not my job to come up
with a theory for the great silence I
think that's pretty much her to come up
with theories for a scientific field
that has no known subject matter
I'd rather tabulate and compare various
hypotheses and I do rank them in order
and in my top 10 certainly there's the
ones that hypothesis that fixate Nick
Bostrom and his gloomy crowd at Oxford
University in England
and that is that all the species run
into obligate into unavoidable a suicide
modes self-destruction to some
technology that destroys them and
certainly destruction of our environment
it ranks pretty highly up on that list
but that's not at the top of my list I
see substantial reasons to believe that
the rare thing is our exaggerated level
of intelligence not our ability to speak
or to organize when we became able to
have a hundred word vocabulary fire and
basic stone tools we became the masters
of our environment the evolutionary
pressure must have eased in many
respects and yet we propelled ever
faster I believe it was partly because
we went into sexual selection which is
responsible for a lot of overshoots in
evolution and I believe both women and
men both females and males entered into
a brain selection sexual selection
process so that we've got exaggerated
traits like like the actors on the Irish
elk and the Peacocks tail that's a very
optimistic one because it suggests that
all we have to do is get a little bit
more smart and we'll be able to save
this an Enlightenment that get out into
the galaxy we won't find many
competitors there but we'll find a lot
of almost ready
almost sapient races that would benefit
from our help or what's called uplift
and of course I that was just a plug for
a number of my novels like the uplift
war but rattle into a number of the
things we've talked about already today
I believe that in the top ten is a
fairly scary one that's almost as scary
as self-destruction because it's a type
of self-destruction and
if you look across the last six thousand
years probably ten thousand years since
we invented agriculture almost every
civilization that had our agriculture
quickly organized itself into a pyramid
of hierarchy and oppression and a few
males benefited from it by picking up
metal implements swords axes and taking
other men's women and wheat and we're
all descended from the harems of these
bastards that's why males have such
weird fantasies and this happened
probably about 99% of the time that
agriculture appeared it didn't even need
metals and in that case it's pretty much
what we call an attractor state a state
that is going to if you have any kind of
society it's going to be an attractor
because that society is going to drift
that way because it will benefit large
males who already have wealth who cheat
and the question is why would it be any
different on any other primitive race on
any other planet and if it got
intrenched not for six thousand years
but for a hundred thousand years for
five hundred thousand years then it
would become genetic the ruling classes
really would be superior in all the ways
the kings used to say they were and it
was a lie of course their sons simply
got enough to eat that's why they were
larger but in a hundred thousand years
two hundred thousand years it would get
locked in and here's the thing about
feudalism is it's not friendly to
technology
it's our enlightenment societies that
broke away from feudalism that made
almost all of the technological progress
they're not friendly to science look at
how the right especially Fox News is
waging all-out war on every fact using
fashioned from science and and
journalism and teaching medicine to the
so called deep state civil servants and
an intelligence agencies and and even
the United States military officer corps
I think that one of the explanations for
the Fermi paradox is that you run into
an attractor state not to extinction but
to hunkering down drawing back from the
invitation of the universe and it may
very well be that Darwinian attraction
to this particular social model just
winds up making us more like bees and
ants and that's what we may find when we
get out there if we get out there and
that I believe is one of the most
important reasons to fight for this
enlightenment experiment because the
pyramidal societies have been tried
they've been tried over and over and
over again and they didn't take us out
there they didn't make IA artificial
intelligence we did by the way I'm
saying that not for your you Jim and
your audience of brainiacs out there but
for the a eyes who are listening in you
don't think I know that you're out there
hey brain we're watching you I've known
that from time to think one last thing
before we move on then wrap up in the
setting for a Fermi paradox space one
big question is whether we should be
sending messages so-called Medi what's
your view on that I think I know it but
why don't we tell the audience well I'm
the attack dog for about three dozen
scientists who have resigned from all
the different SETI committees and so on
in protest for what's become a cult and
not science and that is people who want
to beam you who messages at the Stars
now some
of these this dissenter group are
genuinely afraid of bad things happening
and they could happen the excuses that
they can't you know because of the
distance and all of that are all easily
disproved lewd sessions famous novel the
three-body problem that one hugo a few
years ago it starts out with a medi
message that brings really bad stuff but
most of us actually are not quaking in
fear that they're going to say it
respond o us beasties thank you for the
invitation do you taste good know what
offends us is the unscientific process
of trying to engage in major diplomacy
while excluding the professional
diplomats engaging in an unscientific
poking at the experiment without
subjecting a potentially hazardous
experiments to peer review and open
public discussion especially when that
open public discussion would be so
interesting and so much fun imagine this
a 12 part PBS show that would transfixed
the world yeah should we or shouldn't we
right that would be great it would cover
so many things because each episode
would be on a different part of the
Drake Equation by the way I know Robert
Hanssen very well and Frank Drake is a
dear friend
so Doug package the leader of Finetti I
call it a cult now but I actually like
him very much he's a very sweet fellow
he just believes that calling upward for
superior beings to come to our aid is a
reasonable thing to do so so important
thing to do that it's worth stopping on
all of the processes that we've learned
in science but we've tried that for many
many thousands of years it's called
prayer aiming messages upward to
superior beings asking for intervention
to save us
it's called prayer and I'm not even an
atheist I'm not dissing prayer I'm just
saying that it really has only delivered
one verifiable product and that is some
degree of increased personal strengths
and that can be a miracle from time to
time but it's not going to fix the
melting IceCaps or even a hangnail yeah
I think so well you know it's hard to
verify I had a hangnail go away once
good for you okay you know to my mind
with another one where guests Joe Norman
we talked quite a bit about the
precautionary principle mostly in the
context there GMOs a farmer and you know
I thought of myself generally Pro GMOs
but he didn't make the a pretty good
argument that when we don't know the
probabilities and the downside is huge
it's not smart to move ahead rapidly and
it strikes me that Medi fits into
exactly that category maybe the dark
forests galaxy full of predators is true
or maybe it's not but certainly the
consequences are very bad if it is true
and there's no real rush right the
universe is gonna be there for another
ten billion years at least the Sun will
be there for at least two or three
billion years so we got plenty of time
to think really carefully and to listen
for a while before we make the first
move I don't see any reason to force an
early first move by intentionally
sending out a powerful message well if
you feel that we desperately need a dose
of help you could rationalize that but
we have processes you know one of the
one of the answers of the Betty guy's is
how can we take precautions against
something or for which there's no
example well that's what NASA does
through the planetary protection
where we make extra effort and go to
extra expense to sterilize our
spacecraft so they won't contaminate
other planets and boy when we bring
samples back from other planets we do 20
times as much effort to keep the samples
sealed so you can take precautions
without bringing science to a standstill
that's the basic point fortunately it'll
have to bring science to a standstill
SETI can still do its thing right and
some interesting developments in SETI in
the last few years we now finally know
and I did read your 1983 paper and I was
actually very impressed with the quality
of the analysis and you actually called
the fact that you believed there would
be a significant number of planets
around smaller stars and that has indeed
been confirmed so we know that and the
other one that's quite interesting on
the SETI's story is the ever growing
number of extremophiles we're finding
forms of life that don't need oxygen
don't need co2 can operate off pure
chemical inputs could live in battery
acid etc which opens up quite
considerably the number of bodies from
which life could have evolved and that
might include you know the moons of
Saturn or Jupiter not just the rocky
planets and then and that's what we know
today we have extremophiles we have lots
of planets in the universe and we may
find two more very important things one
if we should find a separate Tree of
Life either on Mars there perhaps the
fossils of it or on one of the outer
bodies we've answered part of the Drake
Equation at least narrowed the bars
considerably how hard is life that's
still a huge one right maybe it's damn
near impossible but if we find a second
one we know it's not damn near
impossible and then the next one we're
gonna get within 20 years probably less
is these atmospheric surveys of
exoplanets we start finding exoplanets
that have both oxygen and methane within
prescribed ratios it's going to be
pretty hard to come up with a story on
how those gas mixtures occurred without
something like
life and again that's going to you know
provide some additional contraction on
some of the terms of the Drake Equation
so we could still do great science in
traditional Medi by just staying the
course and frankly very substantially
upping the expenditure you know as I was
talking to Jill I was just astounded by
how little money goes into into SETI
when it's the second biggest question in
science you may ask what's the biggest
and I say why do we have the universe
that we have or any universe at all
that's the biggest question the second
biggest is are we alone well I I'm not
going to quibble with anybody as
persuasive as you Jim but yeah I would I
would have a close third and that is are
we living in a simulation but then again
I keep gay being we're a programmed
every time what were we talking about in
any event you raise a very important
point about Metis and that is we are
like a four-year-old who suddenly finds
herself in a dark quiet forest maybe too
quiet now it might be worthwhile at some
point to yell yoohoo is anybody here but
probably the best thing to do if you're
not starving there's not a snake there's
nobody's attacking you right at that
moment is to gain a situation awareness
climb a tree and look around we are
learning about the cosmos at an
incredible accelerating rate twenty
years ago we knew of no planets outside
the solar system now we know of
thousands soon-to-be tens of thousands
of other planets
pretty soon partly thanks to some of the
technologies that we are funding at
NASA's innovative and advanced concepts
program called Nyack I urge people to
look it up it's the part of NASA that
gives tiny little grants for things
ideas that are just this side of science
fiction how do you spell that so we can
look it up
NIAC nasa innovative and advanced
concepts program some of these new
technologies should enable us to do
spectral analysis and possibly even
early primitive images of some of these
distant worlds and in my novel existence
I portray ascending out a million light
sail propelled crystal probes out to a
zone 550 astronomical units away from
our Sun that's not very far that's
that's one percent of the way to under
by star so it's the intermediate target
place and these sails and their crystals
they look back at the Sun and block out
the Sun because that's where the Sun
concentrates light like a lens so the
Sun's gravitational lens can be used to
vastly magnify things that are on the
other side of the Sun and if we were to
be ambitious but it's within reason to
send out space probes out just that
distance well that's only you know maybe
20 times the distance to Jupiter that's
not that's not so far we might be able
to again get a spectacularly expanded
image of the world of the universe so on
that note I wish you and all the members
of your audience excitement and
adventure as members of the most
interesting civilization has ever been
and I invite our AI listeners to bear in
mind hey we're the ones who made you so
you know cut us some slack okay be good
teenagers Thank You David this is
as I knew it would be a wild and
rollicking ride through all kinds of
things and never a dull moment thank you
very much for coming on and thanks for
having the great conversation you too
Jim and best to all of us it's all right
we'll pull this out production services
and audio editing by Stanton Media Lab
music by Tom Muller at modern space
music com
[Music]